<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, January 30, 1699/1700 being an anniversary sermon for the day / by William Stephens, B.D. Rector of Sutton in Surry. ; Corrected by the author.</title>
            <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5463A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2275:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, January 30, 1699/1700 being an anniversary sermon for the day / by William Stephens, B.D. Rector of Sutton in Surry. ; Corrected by the author.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 7-29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed: and are to be sold by A. Baldwin, at the Oxford-Arms in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Titus, III, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>STEPHENS</hi>'s SERMON Preach'd Before the HONOURABLE Houſe of Commons, <hi>January</hi> 30th. 1699/1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Honourable Auditory</hi> before whom the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Sermon was Preached, having expreſſed their miſlike, I never deſigned to have had it Printed: But ſince it is ſtolen uncorrectly into the World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my Privity, I hope it will not be imputed as a Crime, that I amend the <hi>Errata</hi> of the Preſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Will. Stephens.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D Before the HONOURABLE <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> January the 30th. 1699/1700. Being an Anniverſary SERMON for the DAY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM STEPHENS,</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Sutton</hi> in <hi>Surry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corrected by the Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed: And are to be Sold by <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> at the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="editor_to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:3"/>
            <head>THE EDITOR TO THE PREACHER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SINCE the <hi>Printer</hi> inform'd me, that he will make a Second Impreſſion of your Sermon, I thought it might be fit to offer you ſome Satisfaction for Printing it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your Conſent. For although I was told, that you were obſtinate in refuſing to Print it, yet I thought it might be uſeful to the Publick, and no ways diſſerviceable to You to Publiſh it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, having gotten a Copy, I gave it to a Printer, only with this Charge, that he ſhould make the Impreſſion as Cheap as he could, for as I obſerv'd, that the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it made you ſome Enemies, ſo I concluded that the Printing of it might Gain You ſome Friends; becauſe the Miſrepreſentations which were given Abroad concerning it would vaniſh away.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:4"/>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Reflection</hi> which was made upon You by a Suppoſititious Clergyman, I Appeal my Ld. A. Bp. of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> if he did not receive Satisfaction from a Worthy Member of Parliament, being a Man of unſpotted Reputation, that what was objected againſt You by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecter</hi> as to your flying from a ſuſpected Proſecution, was wholly <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Scandalous.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, I wiſh you well,</salute> and am
<signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151758:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>TITUS III. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates; and to be ready to every good Work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TO underſtand the Reaſon of this, and ſuch-like Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, which frequently occur in the Apoſtle's Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Two Things may be premiſed:</p>
            <p n="1">I. That about the Time of our Saviour Chriſt, there aroſe one <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi> (who is mention'd <hi>Acts</hi> 5.37.) preaching Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditrous Doctrines to the People, and teaching, (as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> in his Comment on my Text obſerves,) That they ought to own no Sovereign Prince, but God alone: And if they pay'd their Tithes to the Prieſt, they were diſcharg'd from paying Tribute to the Emperor. And upon this Account it was (as St. <hi>Jerom</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved) that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ask'd our Saviour that captious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Is it lawful to give Tribute to Caeſar, or no?</hi> Matth. 22.17. Now to this Account <hi>Anastaſius Nicenus</hi> adds, That the Followers of this <hi>Judas</hi> were very numerous, and called by the Name of <hi>Gallileans,</hi> and commonly looked upon as Men ill affected to the <hi>Roman</hi> Government: Particularly, becauſe, when they offered Sacrifice, they refuſed to make Supplication for the Emperor and People of <hi>Rome;</hi> upon which Account it is thought that <hi>Pilate,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Deputy of <hi>Judea, came upon them whilst they were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing, and putting them to the ſword; mingled their blood with the blood of the ſacrifices;</hi> as you may read, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151758:5"/>
            <p>And from hence it was, that our Saviour Chriſt and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were ſuſpected of favouring Seditious Doctrines, becauſe they came out of <hi>Galilee,</hi> as is obſerved by St. <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> in his 23d. <hi>Homile on the Romans,</hi> wherein he ſaith, That great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports were ſpread abroad, as if the Diſciples were a Factious, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious People, and deſigning againſt the Government. It muſt alſo be confeſſed, that many of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were converted to the Chriſtian Faith, were not ſufficiently reſpectful to the higher Powers which God's Providence had ſet over them: For which Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> gives this Reaſon, Since the Powers that were then in Being oppoſed themſelves to our Saviour Chriſt, they thought them unworthy of Reſpect and Honour.</p>
            <p>Now what hath been ſaid concerning the <hi>Gallilean</hi> Perſuaſion, ſhews the Reaſon why the Apoſtles do ſo frequently in their Letters direct the Chriſtian Churches to Loyalty, or a due Submiſſion to Magiſtrates.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To clear themſelves from the falſe and ſcandalous Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of having imbib'd the Doctrine of <hi>Judas</hi> the <hi>Gallilean.</hi> And,</item>
               <item>2. To undeceive all thoſe that had been perverted by that ſeditious Doctrine.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">II. The Second Thing I would premiſe, is, That about the Time when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, the People of <hi>Crete</hi> (which was <hi>Titus</hi> his Dioceſs) were unruly and mutinous. <hi>Grotius</hi> ſays, That they were always a factious People; and for that Reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote to <hi>Titus,</hi> their Biſhop, to <hi>put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, and to be ready to every good Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I ſhall take Occaſion from hence, Firſt, To make a juſt Comment upon the Text.</item>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151758:5"/>
               <item>II. To ſet forth the Reaſons and Grounds upon which the Apoſtles founded their Doctrine of Obedience to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrates. And,</item>
               <item>III. To apply theſe Reaſons in Conjunction with the Occaſion of this Day's Humiliation. And,</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. Firſt, It may be obſerv'd, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>Titus</hi> to teach the Doctrine of Civil Obedience as a new Thing, but only to refreſh their Memories therewith, <hi>to put them in mind,</hi> &amp;c. For Men cannot be ſuppoſed ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the abſolute Neceſſity of Government, to the Defence and Support of Society; which were, in effect, to ſuppoſe, that 'twere better to lead the Lives of Beaſts than Men, and that the World were willing to lie under the continual Calamity of War and Opreſſion, fill'd only with a Rout of Fools and Madmen. 'Twere to ſuppoſe every ſingle Perſon willing to expoſe himſelf to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controll'd World, and bid defiance to the unbounded Power, Rage, and Malice of Mankind. We cannot but ſee our ſelves link'd together by Common Wants into Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Societies, and that theſe Societies cannot ſubſiſt, unleſs they are upheld by the Power of Government, whoſe Wiſdom and Juſtice muſt appear by a due Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good Laws: And from hence we cannot but ſee a Neceſſity of <hi>Principalities and Powers,</hi> of Superior and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> without whom Laws can be neither made nor executed. From whence 'tis very viſible, that Subjection to a good Government is as much our Intereſt as it is our Duty. This was evident to the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Sect of old, who would not ſuffer the Blood of any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151758:6"/> Creature to be ſhed for their uſe, but yet allow'd the Sword of the Magiſtrate to cut off Malefactors.</p>
            <p>The following Words in my Text, are, <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers.</hi> Now the Word in the Original ſignifying ſomething which is Prime and Principal, muſt denote the Supreme Eſtabliſh'd Power, from whence Inferior Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities are derived, and is the ſame with the <hi>higher Powers</hi> mentioned <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. But becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Principalities and Powers</hi> in the <hi>Plural</hi> Number, 'tis likely that he alludes to the Diſtinction (which was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among the <hi>Romans</hi>) of the greater and leſſer Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the former of which, during the Commonwealth, were the Conſuls, Pretors, and Cenſors; all which Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Time, were veſted in the Emperor, and made up the Imperial Dignity. The leſſer Powers were all thoſe derived from hence, and were ſubordinate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And this Diſtinction was ſo nicely obſerv'd among the <hi>Romans,</hi> that <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> puniſh'd a Tribune, becauſe he ſuffered himſelf to be ſtiled one of the higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Sueton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the Text it muſt be obſerv'd, that our Obedience becomes due, not only to the Supreme, but Inferior Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities; for the <hi>Cretans,</hi> to whom <hi>Titus</hi> preached the Goſpel, were part of a <hi>Roman</hi> Province, governed by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Officers, deputed from <hi>Rome,</hi> who were the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates they were exhorted to obey. For tho the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior and inferior Powers differ greatly, if compared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves; yet, with reſpect to the Subjects Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, they are to be regarded alike; ſo that we cannot wilfully diſobey the Inferior, without affronting the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151758:6"/> Authority. If then the <hi>Cretans</hi> would obey the Emperor, it muſt be by Submiſſion to the Ordinances and Officers which he had appointed to their Iſland; and if they behaved themſelves ſuitably to theſe Magiſtrates, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged their Duty to the Imperial Power which depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them.</p>
            <p>We ſee that a large Family cannot be governed by the Perſonal Preſence of the Maſter, much leſs can an Empire; ſo that there will be need to call in to the Prince's Aſſiſtance, ſuch Perſons into whom he may diffuſe ſome meaſure of his Political Soul, and thereby unite them as Members to his own Body-Politick; whereupon they are to be treated as the Hands, Arms and Eyes of Majeſty: And hence <hi>Titus</hi> admoniſhed them, not only to <hi>be ſubject to Principalities and Powers,</hi> but <hi>to obey Magistrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The Second Thing I propoſed to ſpeak to, were the Reaſons upon which the Apoſtles grounded their Doctrine of Civil Obedience; which are Two:</p>
            <p>The one is given by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who teaches, That, <hi>Every Soul ſhould be ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> becauſe <hi>The Magiſtrate is the Minister of God to us for good,</hi> Rom. 13.1, 4.</p>
            <p>The Second Reaſon is given by St. <hi>Peter, viz.</hi> Becauſe all Governments and Governours do ariſe from our own Conſent, <hi>Submit your ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to every ordinance of man, for the Lord's ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupreme,</hi> &amp;c. Where note, That the King is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151758:7"/> called the Ordinance, or Creature of Man, becauſe the Sovereign Power it ſelf is veſted in Men, according to Humane Compact: And from hence our Subjection is urg'd by the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in his 1<hi>st Epist.</hi> 2<hi>d Chapter, Verſe</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Argument, who calls Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy a Divine Ordinance, becauſe of the excellent Uſe of it, whereby good Magiſtrates reſemble the Divine Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs, in ſecuring to all Men their Rights and Properties; in preſerving the Peace, Health and Safety of Societies, both with reſpect to Body and Soul. But to be more particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Preſervation of Property was the firſt benefit for which Magiſtracy was deſigned.</hi> Now Property is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally attained by the Labour of either Body or Mind; for ſuppoſing the Earth to have been common to its Firſt Inhabitants, it will follow that whoever took the Pains to cultivate any part of it, and lay up neceſſary Stores for his uſe, had by this his Induſtry made himſelf the true Proprietor thereof. And could we ſuppoſe this New Proprietor to be as well guarded, as that Man we read of in the Goſpel, <hi>who was well Armed, and kept his Pallace and Goods in Peace,</hi> yet it may likewiſe be ſuppoſed, (as it there follows) <hi>that if a ſtronger than he ſhall come upon him, he will take from him all his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour wherein he truſted, and divide his Spoils.</hi> And this uncertain condition of Property ſhews the reaſon of Mens uniting into Societies, and ſetting up Forms of Government, which is for Mutual Defence and Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Property: And that, not only for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151758:7"/> of the preſent Poſſeſſors, but of Future Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So that, what becomes a Man's own, either by Labour, Gift or Purchace, may with Safety be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by himſelf, and alſo conveied down to his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Life and Limbs are ours by the Gift of God. And theſe Properties are liable to be invaded and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: Tho' they cannot (like other Goods) be trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to the uſe of the Spoiler. And ſince there is ſo much Variance and Malice, Pride and Strife among Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, what ill offices may not one Man apprehend from another? But when deſtructive Malice, a Fiend of Hell, ſhall transform it ſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Men that they are then inſpired with the Spirit of God, when they are poſſeſſed by the <hi>Apollyon,</hi> the great Enemy and Deſtroyer of Mankind, when under the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion it ſelf, Men ſhall exert their ſharpeſt Malice, not only againſt the Poſſeſſions and Liberties, but againſt the Lives of one another; how great need is there of the Magiſtrates interpoſing Power to diſarm them of their Spiritual as well as Carnal Weapons of Warfare, to take away the Ball of Contention from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and the power of evil-doing from all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Parties? And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. In this the Magiſtrate is God's Miniſter to us for good, not only with reſpect to the Preſervation of our Liberties and Lives from Deſtruction, but of our Souls from Sin; for whilſt this Juſt Liberty, this Natural Right of worſhipping God, according to that Knowledge He hath given us, is ſupported by Law, no Man is forced
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151758:8"/> into hypocritical Compliances, contrary to the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Conſcience, but every one may worſhip the One True God in ſingleneſs of Heart; whereas on the other hand, if in Matters of Religion, Force be ſuffered to take the Place of Reaſon, all Religions will be alike, and (as Colours in the Dark) undiſtinguiſhable.</p>
            <p>And altho the Magiſtrate can beſtow no Divine Grace upon the Souls of Men, yet whilſt by puniſhing Vice, Immoral Practices are reſtrained, he prevents the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of Sin in a Land. And if ceaſing to do Evil, be one ſtep towards learning to do well, whilſt the Civil Powers reſtrain us from Immoralities, they turn us out of the Broad way of Perdition into the Paths of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Peace.</p>
            <p>From hence then it appears, <hi>That they who are wanting in their Submiſſion and Aſſiſtance to the Civil Miniſtry of God, are falſe to their own Intereſt, as well as that of their Poſterity.</hi> Whereas on the other hand, he who is ready to every <hi>good work</hi> which may ſupport this Divine Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry to us for good, will be ſure, in the Performance of his Duty, to find his Account.</p>
            <p>Let us then take a View of our Goods and Chattels, Houſes and Lands, Wives and Children; let us conſider the Bleſſings of Health, Safety and Liberty: Let us think how to preſerve our Lives from Deſtruction, our Souls from Sin: Whether we Eat or Drink, or Sleep or Wake, or whatever we do with Comfort or Safety, we hereby diſcover our Continual Obligation to the good Magiſtrates Care over us, wherby we are <hi>put in mind to be ſubject,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151758:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. The other Reaſon of Submiſſion given by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is, <hi>Becauſe all Governments and Governours ariſe from the Peoples Conſent.</hi> They are the Ordinances and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men, the Creatures of Humane Compact. For we do not find <hi>That God did appoint any Form of Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government for a Pattern to be follow'd by any Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty now in Being upon the Earth.</hi> We ſee no ſuch Rule in the Book of Nature; Nor do we read in Scripture of any particular Polity preſcribed to all, or any People, now imbodied in the World. We read there, That all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments and Governours are appointed by God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi> &amp;c. But we find no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Adminiſtration, no Particular Family, or Single Perſon, now in Being, ordained to Government by Divine Precept: But each Magiſtrate and Magiſtracy is left to the Ordinance and Appointment of thoſe Men who have joined themſelves together in Society.</p>
            <p>The great Variety we ſee in Civil Government, ſhews, <hi>That they are all the Effects of Humane Contrivance, and ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Several Intereſts of the Reſpective Societies:</hi> Thus the Ancient Charter of the Neighbouring City, Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all thoſe uſeful and neceſſary Powers, by which ſo great a Body is governed, Was it not the wiſe Contrivance of their Anceſtors? And did it not receive its Eſtabliſhment from the Principalities and Powers of the Realm? And the Great Charter of the Realm it ſelf is no more than the wiſe Ordinance of our Fore-fathers? And the Dates of its Royal Confirmations are ſtill remaining among us. And as ſeveral ſmaller Societies have their Free Cuſtoms diſtinct from one another; ſo in different Nations there are various Lodgments, even of the Sovereign Power, which appear to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151758:9"/> be the Effects of Free-will: becauſe in every rational Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſomething may be obſerved which is peculiar and diſtinguiſhing.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, Have we not ſeen the forms of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment even in the ſame Nations changed from what they formerly had been? As in <hi>Sweden, France, and Denmark.</hi> And have not our eyes beheld of late Years, the Legal Form of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy degenerated into Tyranny, and again recovered, through God's Bleſſing, together with the Courage and Conduct of the Man of his own Right Hand, who by reſtoring our Ancient Liberties, juſtly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended himſelf to the Imperial Crown of this Realm by the Free Conſent of the People?</p>
            <p>Nor was it otherwiſe of old, when <hi>Moſes</hi> was by Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Miracle recommended of God to be the Father of his Country. For tho by a Divine Power he wrought out <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Deliverance from <hi>Egypt</hi> by Conducting them into the Wilderneſs, yet there was no Form of Government eſtabliſhed among the Tribes till <hi>Jethro</hi> made a Viſit to his Son in Law <hi>Moſes,</hi> to whoſe Counſel it was owing that a ſound Polity was ſet up in the Land of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For inſtead of the whole burden of the Government lying upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> which <hi>Jethro</hi> told him <hi>was not good,</hi> he directs him <hi>to provide out of all the People, able men, ſuch as fear God, Men of truth, hating Covetouſneſs, and place ſuch over them to be Rulers over Thouſands, Rulers of Hundreds, Rulers of Fifties and Rulers of Tens, And let them Judge the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at all ſeaſons. And it ſhall be</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jethro</hi>) <hi>that every great matter they ſhall bring unto thee, but every ſmall matter they ſhall judge: Exod.</hi> 18, 17, 21, 22. Thus the burden
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151758:9"/> of the Civil Government ſhould ſit eaſie upon the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and the People ſhould receive a quick diſpatch of their Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> (as you read) follows this advice, and joyns himſelf with the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the choice of Perſons fit for this Adminiſtration, as will appear by comparing the 25th <hi>verſe</hi> of the forecited Chapter with the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Deut.</hi> In the former <hi>verſe</hi> we read that <hi>Moſes choſe able Men out of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and made them Heads over the People.</hi> But the latter place ſhews that the Peoples Conſent was had in the election of theſe Officers. For ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats the Circumſtances of that Action, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.9. &amp;c. <hi>And I ſpake unto you at that time ſaying, I am not able to bare you my ſelf alone,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>take ye therefore wiſe Men and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and known among your Tribes, and I will make them Rulers over you.</hi> From hence it appears.
<list>
                  <item>1. That the Old Conſtitution of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Government, was the Contrivance of <hi>Jethro</hi> an <hi>Heathen,</hi> and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates who were in the Adminiſtration were choſen by the Joint Conſent of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the People. And,</item>
                  <item>2. That no one Perſon, tho never ſo able, ſo Wiſe, and Valiant as <hi>Moſes,</hi> is ſufficient to Govern a Nation without the Advice and joint Aſſiſtance of Inferiour Magiſtrates. Much leſs ſuch a Man who hath no pretence to the Spirit and Character of this Divine Legiſlator.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It has been thought by ſome, that a great Conqueror might form a Civil Government in a conquer'd Nation, without the Conſent of the People by the ſole Power of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151758:10"/> own Will. And ſuppoſe it were ſo, then that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would be an Humane Ordinance, becauſe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror is but a Man. But I deny it to be poſſible for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Conqueror, tho never ſo great, to make himſelf a King over any People without their Conſent. For to let paſs what our Hiſtories tell us of the Capitulations which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the reſpective Conqueſt of the <hi>Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> before they erected any Form of Government in this Land. Let us ſuppoſe that a Great General, with a powerful Foreign Army, ſhould ſo far over run a Nation that the People thereof could not be able to make any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Reſiſtance; in ſuch a Caſe the Relations of <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Slave</hi> are actually introduc'd by the Conqueſt. The Conquerors are <hi>Lords</hi> and the Natives <hi>Slaves:</hi> But then this State is a State of War ſtill, but no Political or Civil Conſtitution. The Abſolute <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>Slave</hi> are as yet, upon no civil Terms with one another, no Obligations have as yet paſſed between them, but they are both left to their own Wills; and if the Lord may take away the Life of his Slave, the Slave is under no Obligation of dealing otherwiſe with his Lord. So that if this Great General intends to rule in Peace over the Conquer'd People he will find himſelf conſtrained to enter into ſome Terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact with them, upon which they are willing to accept him for the Head of their Government, and Oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to obey him. But put the Caſe that a Nation, to avoid preſent Deſtruction, would Conſent to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Legal Slaves, this can no more oblige them than an honeſt Man is bound to keep Promiſe with a barbarous Highway-man; for iniquity cannot be eſtabliſh'd by a Law, much leſs can it bind Poſterity, of whoſe Lives and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties they had no Right to diſpoſe. And Conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151758:10"/> they may juſtly reſtore themſelves to a State of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom when ever they are able.</p>
            <p>And if a mighty Conqueror cannot attain a Civil Power over a Conquer'd People without their Conſent, how ſhall he obtain it over his own Conquering Nation, without their free Concurrence? Did this Victorious People leave their Native Country, with all the Liberties they injoy'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to follow their Chief into a Foreign Land, wherein they hoped to find a better Settlement for themſelves and Poſterity; would they indure all the Hardſhips of War, and by their Sweat and Blood purchaſe an intire Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt that they might be reduced to the miſerable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Conquer'd People? that is, to become Slaves to their General. I allow, that this Chief may by the help of his own People, make himſelf own'd by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd upon advantageous Terms. But by what inviſible power ſhall he gain to be (I will not ſay abſolute Maſter but even) the Civil Head over his new ſettled Colony? It can be nothing elſe but their own free Conſent which can Inveſt him with a Political Headſhip over them. And then, how great Reaſon have they to Pay a due Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to that Ordinance which themſelves have made, and to ſubmit to Principalities and Powers which were their own Appointment, and for their own Benefit?</p>
            <p n="3">III. Having thus ſet forth the Apoſtolical Grounds of Civil Obedience, I crave leave to make ſome improvement of them: Firſt By way of General Application, for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on the diſmal Effects of this Days Tragedy (with which you have been Annually acquainted all your Lives) would be ſuperfluous Labour. And therefore I ſhall rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151758:11"/> 
               <hi>to offer ſome Cautions which may probably prevent the like Miſchiefs for the future.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi>ſt.</hi> The Apoſtolical Reaſons of Obedience being duly conſider'd, may ſerve to allay the Fears and Jealouſies of ſome Good Men, who have conceived, That a National Government hath not ſo ſure a Foundation as is neceſſary, if it be only bottom'd upon Humane Compact: Becauſe Mens Minds being ſubject to frequent Alterations, all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments will, as they think, be very unſteady.</p>
            <p>And it muſt be acknowledged, That in all dubious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherein the Judgment cannot come to a Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Minds of Men will be unſettled. So likewiſe in ſmaller matters, ſcarce worthy of ſerious Deliberation, Men will act differently. Nay, in Matters of Moment, ſome Men may ſuffer themſelves to be Carry'd away by unaccountable Capricio's: But yet none of theſe things can any ways endanger a Conſtitution ſettled upon the Foundations before mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe a Good Government is a Matter of ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Importance, that no Man in his Wits can doubt, whether he ſhall concur to its Support or not. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, The Compact by which all Governours are intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, is evermore Solemn and Deliberate; and attended with the strongest Tye to the Sovereign Power by which 'tis poſſible for a man to ratifie the Solemn Obligations he has Contracted.</hi> For ſuch a Bond is, <hi>The Oath of the Lord;</hi> by which the Allegiance of the Subject is confirmed. And if a Deliberate Compact, freely enter'd into, upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151758:11"/> the wiſeſt and ſtrongeſt Motives of Advantage, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Solemn Oaths and Promiſes, be not a ſufficient Eſtabliſhment, 'tis hard to ſay what is ſuch. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome Men may ſuffer themſelves to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away from a Uſeful and Neceſſary Eſtabliſhment, by Reaſonings contrary to the General Stream of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it cannot be preſum'd that the Number and Abilities of ſuch Men will ever be ſufficient to unhinge any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable Adminiſtration of a Government thus Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Indeed, Nothing but an Abſolute Neceſſity, and ſuch as is viſible in an extraordinary manner, will be effectual to work a Change in any Settled Conſtitution, ſuch an One, as renders Mankind fully ſatisfied, without the leaſt remaining Scruple, that the Government then in Being, is not the Ordinance of God to them for Good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From what hath been ſaid it alſo appears, <hi>That no Man's Pretence to the Memberſhip of any pure Apoſtolick Church, can excuſe, much leſs warrant his Diſaffection to that Government which God's Providence, and Man's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent have ſet over a People for their Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſpeak this to take away that Scandal which ſome have endeavoured to fix upon the <hi>Church of England;</hi> as if ſhe had laid any Obligation upon her Sons, in Oppoſition to the Preſent Conſtitution: Whereas the contrary Truth is Self-Evident. For does not our Church, in Her <hi>Sixth Article,</hi> receive all the Books of the New Teſtament, as they are commonly receiv'd, and account them Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal? Is not my Text part of that Canon? And are not all our Biſhops and Clergy thereby obliged, as much as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151758:12"/> 
               <hi>Titus</hi> was, to put their Hearers in mind of their <hi>Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Principalities and Powers?</hi> Or can we pretend to be Members of an Apoſtolical Church, if we carry our ſelves unſeemly towards ſuch a Government, whoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration directly tends to our Common Good, and was alſo our own Ordinance and Appointment, which are the Apoſtolical Reaſons of Civil Obedience?</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this, as if by Vertue of the Miniſterial Function we could pretend to preſcribe Forms of Civil Government to Nations, to determine the <hi>Regalia</hi> of Princes, or the ſubordinate Powers of inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. <hi>The Book of God</hi> does not furniſh us with Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for this Work, much leſs require it of us. It injoins us to make Peace among our Neighbours, by indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to incline Mens Minds to a peaceable Temper; but it does not inable us to judge the leaſt Point of Legal Right which is in Controverſie between them; much leſs does it teach us to determine the Rights, Titles or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Princes and Magiſtrates; but yet it injoins us to <hi>put men in mind to be ready to every good work,</hi> which may contribute to ſupport a Good Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the Doctrine already ſet forth, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Misfortunes of that Sovereign Prince which are this Day called to Remembrance, ariſeth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Caution to Two ſorts of People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To all thoſe who have the Honour to ſhare the Publick Adminiſtration, that they make it their Equal Care that the Government which at preſent we enjoy, may be always <hi>the Ministry of God to us for good.</hi> For ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151758:12"/> an Adminiſtration applies the Text in the moſt ſenſible manner, convincing every one that he ought to be <hi>ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates, and to be ready to every good work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well known, That the Character of a Good Prince is raiſed ſo high in the Holy Scripture, that ſuch are called <hi>Gods upon Earth;</hi> to admoniſh them of that continual over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing Kindneſs, that univerſal Beneficence, that tender Care and Concern for their Peoples Welfare, which their High Office requires. And from the Scriptures we are alſo informed, That the kind Providences of God are immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately conveied to Men by his holy Angels, who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Ministring Spirits, Hebrews</hi> 1.14. and are moſt eſpecially employed in Works of Deliverance. By their Means <hi>Lot</hi> was delivered out of <hi>Sodom, Iſaac</hi> from the Arm that was ſtretched forth to make him a Sacrifice, <hi>Iſrael</hi> was conducted through the Wilderneſs to <hi>Canaan, Elijah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from Famine, and at laſt carried from Earth to Heaven. By their Means <hi>Daniel</hi> was delivered from the Lions, and the Three <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the fiery Furnace. Theſe were the Heralds who firſt Publiſhed the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World by our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe delivered <hi>Peter</hi> from his Chains, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> from their Impriſonment. Whereby a Pattern is ſet up to the <hi>Ministry</hi> of a Great and Good Prince; who are hereby di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Cultivate and Adorn that Deliverance which their <hi>Great Master</hi> hath wrought out for his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> By being the firſt Meſſengers and Promoters of thoſe Methods which may for ever hereafter ſecure our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties from danger of Relapſe.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151758:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly</hi> By a diligent avoiding of all thoſe Methods by which the Glory of former Princes has been Eclipſed, and the Hearts of their People alienated from them.</p>
            <p>The ſubordinate Miniſtry is the Viſible Majeſty of the King, whereby he is made known to his People, and more eſpecially in time of Peace; For, tho during a War, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Courage and Conduct of a Great Prince is made very Publick, whilſt his Perſon is Expoſed to the View of Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes; yet when Peace ſhall reſtore him to a more Private State of Life, His Perſonal Endowments, tho never ſo Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in themſelves, cannot become Viſible to the Body of a People, any other way than by the conſtant Care and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, the Great Diligence and Publick Spirit of thoſe to whom he hath committed the Truſt of His People's Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: The want of this Neceſſary Concern for <hi>Publick Good,</hi> did, in ſome meaſure, aſſiſt in bringing on that Tragical Scene, which is this Day Commemorated. As 'tis common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen, that Men in a Private Condition of Life are reduced to Great Miſeries, by the Male-Adminiſtration of thoſe to whom they had committed their private Truſts.</p>
            <p>But when a <hi>Publick Ministry</hi> ſhall join together Hearts and Hands, only to promote the <hi>Publick Weal,</hi> without the leaſt Deſign of warping the <hi>Princes Favour</hi> towards any one <hi>Party of Men,</hi> which like the Light of the Sun, and Breathings of the Air, is deſigned for Common Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Refreſhment, no Jealouſies, Fears or Disaffections can ariſe; 'twill then be impoſſible for the moſt wicked and malicious to diſturb the <hi>Publick Peace,</hi> but the King's Throne will be <hi>establiſhed in righteouſneſs,</hi> and the Voice of the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> will be, <hi>O King live for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151758:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Second Caution affects all thoſe who are concerned <hi>for the Body of the People,</hi> that they let ſlip no Opportunity wherein <hi>Publick Advantages</hi> are offered to them. The Supream Magiſtrate is the greateſt <hi>Miniſter of God to us for good:</hi> But God himſelf is not wont to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force His Kindneſs upon us; but <hi>expects our own Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for our own Behoof:</hi> And when a Gracious Prince ſhall make it appear, both by <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Facts,</hi> that He <hi>cannot have any ſeparate Intereſt from that of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> When He ſhews himſelf <hi>ready to every good work</hi> which is <hi>esteemed beneficial to His People,</hi> tho' his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance therewith may be Complicated with ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Self-Denial, 'twould be a Matter of ſad Reflection, if the <hi>Publick Weal</hi> ſhould not be improv'd by the Advantages which <hi>ſo Good and Gracious an Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation adminiſters unto us.</hi> An Unanimous Conſent in any Matter of <hi>Publick Benefit</hi> will certainly procure it. <hi>To know what is good for us, is to attain it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo One Rule which our Saviour Chriſt has left with us, tending to the Improvement of Knowledge, which when reduced to Practice, will ſuffer no man to be <hi>ignorant of what is good and fit to be done;</hi> 'tis only to carry a <hi>ſingle Eye</hi> about us, according to what is ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.22. <hi>The light of the Body is the Eye, if therefore thine Eye be ſingle, thy whole body ſhall be full of Light:</hi> If the Eye of a man be carried on ſingly (without any biaſing Affection) towards either Publick or Private Good, he will certainly diſcover the Good which he looked for. But if in the Search after Publick Weal, any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate By-Ends be aimed at, if a Private Love to our Selves,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151758:14"/> or a Particular Reſentment againſt any <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Parties,</hi> ſhall over-rule, if either the Admiration or Diſeſteem of others, ſhall incline Men to refuſe <hi>Good Proviſions,</hi> or embrace <hi>Suſpicious Propoſals,</hi> if any thing beſides a <hi>ſincere Deſire to promote the Publick Weal,</hi> ſhall bear Sway in a <hi>Publick Council,</hi> 'tis no ſtrange thing if <hi>Darkneſs</hi> ſhall be called <hi>Light,</hi> and <hi>Light Darkneſs</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may alſo be obſerved, That amongſt the many Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications which have recommended our Holy Religion, no one has more forced its way among Serious and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering Men, than <hi>Its being ſo admirably adapted to the Happineſs of Mankind, and the Good of Societies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unbelievers have denied its <hi>Miracles,</hi> and its <hi>Myſteries</hi> have been diſputed and derided by <hi>Sceptical</hi> and <hi>Profane Men.</hi> But the greateſt Oppoſers of the Chriſtian Name, can neither Deny nor Diſpute the Real Tendency of <hi>Meekneſs, Moderation, Punctual Justice,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Good-Will,</hi> to make men live well one with another, <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to others as we would have them to do to us,</hi> and <hi>lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our very enemies,</hi> leave no Room either for Private Oppreſſion, or Publick Diſturbance. The Spirit of this Religion will not ſuffer us to perpetuate Animoſities, or carry on Suſpicions too far: To think that Men who have once been in the wrong, can never be convinced, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver repent of their Errors: 'Twill ſuffer no Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to hinder from a due Conſideration of any <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals</hi> in behalf of <hi>Publick Good,</hi> from whatever Quarter they may come: Where the <hi>ſingle Eye</hi> is thus directed in a Strait Line towards the Publick Weal, the <hi>Whole Body of ſuch a Council will be full of Light,</hi> whereby they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151758:14"/> will certainly diſcover <hi>the things which belong to our Peace.</hi> Theſe things can never be hid, when a Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are thus in Queſt of them.</p>
            <p>God forbid therefore, <hi>That this Day of ſolemn Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation ſhould be made <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of to flatter Princes with No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Arbitrary Power, by drawing any Concluſions from the Ancient Government of Gods peculiar People, which may Colour over Modern Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid! That the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperial Power in the hands of <hi>Claudius</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> ſhould be own'd as God's Miniſtry, under which the Apoſtles of Chriſt ſuffered Martyrdome. To entertain People with the Melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts of Fetters and Chains, which when laid upon them by ill Princes, yet they muſt not indeavour to remove under Penalty of Eternal Damnation, tends only to exaſperate Humane Nature, and make way for ſuch another Day of Humiliation as that we are now Celebrating: Which, may Divine Goodneſs, for ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent! God forbid, that this day ſhould be made uſe of to continue Heats and Animoſities among us, which ought long ſince to have been buried in Oblivion. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when the Tragical Scene of this Day, was not then the Act of the whole Nation, and few Spectators of it, ſcarce any Actors in it, are now remaining.</p>
            <p>But ſince the Condition of the Greateſt Men upon Earth is ſubject to ſuch <hi>Fatal Cataſtrophe's,</hi> as that was which this Day brings to mind. I cannot but Lament the unhappy Fate of thoſe Princes who are born in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and bred in Luxury, incompaſs'd with Flatterers,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151758:15"/> and ſo intoxicated with the Gaudy Ornaments of Power, as to forget the End for which they were elevated, and made Gods upon Earth. They little conſider that this Greatneſs is ſupported by the Inheritance of the Gentleman, the Hazard of the Merchant, and the Sweat of the Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; who readily Contribute out of their ſmall ſtock to ſupport a Government they themſelves have ſet up. Who are contented to part with their Natural Liberty to thoſe who formerly (it may be) were their Equals, for their Common Good and Protection; which is the only End of Government. A due reflection hereon would make them firſt of all adore the Goodneſs of God whoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath ſo diſtinguiſhed them, and alſo love and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh that Society of Men, who hath raiſed them to ſo high a Station, and ſubmitted themſelves and their Fortunes, in a great meaſure, to their Diſcretion. Then the World would ſee the beſt Men in the higheſt Places, Senates in Authority, Magiſtrates in Eſteem, and the Temple of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue the only Paſſage to that of Honour. Ambition and Corruption will be out of Countenance, and the World will Triumph in an undiſturbed Felicity. The Prince will be happy in the Reverence and Eſteem of his People, and the People ſafe in the Generoſity of the Prince.</p>
            <p>All this and more we may expect from His Majeſty's moſt Happy Reign, who was not (like others) nurſed up in Flattery, but taſted early of the Cup of Affliction, that his Greatneſs might be owing to his own Courage, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Integrity, and not the Uncertain Gift of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Wiſe by Nature, improv'd by Early Adverſity, and conſummated by long Experience in all the Paths of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151758:15"/> Greatneſs; a Prince Lov'd and Obey'd by his own Subjects, Honour'd by his Allies, Dreaded by his Enemies, and will be Admired by late Poſterity.</p>
            <p>Nor do I here inſiſt upon His Great Performances in the Art of War, in which other Princes have had their ſhare, and are often themſelves the wretched Trophy's, erected upon the Tears of miſerable Men. But in his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Years, to reſtore his Native Country, and ſince that, the Liberties of Three moſt Potent Nations, are Glories Peculiar to Himſelf, and cannot be Equall'd by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of the moſt Renowned Chiefs, either of the <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Graecian,</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchs. And to Conſummate all the Felicity that can happen to Mortal-Man, it hath been a Particular Honour reſerv'd by Providence for Him alone, that as where-ever He ſate his Foot, Slavery fled before Him like a Phantome, ſo in His Dominions and under His Protection, are almoſt all the remains of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty now known in the World.</p>
            <p>Not that I ſpeak this, or any thing elſe I have here ſaid, for your Information, (for I know from what <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Aſſembly</hi> I ought to receive Inſtruction) but as my Text directed me, for your Remembrance.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151758:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
